A Finding Aid to the Evangeline J. Montgomery Papers, 1928-2018, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Evangeline J. Montgomery papers
1928-2018
Archives of American Art
Montgomery, Evangeline J.
AAA.montevan
Archival Resource Key
26.1 Linear feet
The papers of African American artist, curator, and arts administrator Evangeline "EJ" Montgomery measure 26.1 linear feet and date from 1929-2019. The papers relate to Montgomery's career and involvement in the African American art scene in California and Washington, D.C. The collection includes biographical materials consisting of calendars and appointment books, certificates and awards, records regarding Montgomery's personal art collection, resumes and biographies, and other personal records; correspondence with colleagues and friends such as Benny Andrews, Willis Bing Davis, Edmund Barry Gaither, Eugene Grigsby, Dele Jegede, Samella Lewis, Nzegwu Nkiru, and A.M. Weaver; professional activity files documenting Montgomery's career as a consultant, curator, member, and volunteer for a myriad of organizations including the American Association for State and Local History, National Conference of Artists, and the Oakland Museum; and research files and notes on African and African American arts and history, Black media, Black photographers, the museum profession, and the artists Betye Saar, Lois Mailou Jones, Nike Davies-Okundaye, Romare Bearden, Ruth Waddy, Sam Gilliam, and Sargent Johnson. Also included are files regarding Montgomery's career as an artist containing material on the Brandywine Workshop, interviews with Floyd Coleman and for The Historymakers, sales and consignment records, and other material; printed and documentary material consisting of art reproductions, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and posters regarding Montgomery and other African American artists; artwork by Montgomery, including student sketchbooks, and others; photographic material of Montgomery, friends and colleagues, events, personal snapshots, and works of art; and unidentified audiovisual material.
Biographical / Historical
Evangeline "EJ" Montgomery (1930- ) is an African American artist, curator, and arts administrator in California and Washington, D.C.
Montgomery was born in New York and moved to Harlem in New York City after the divorce of her parents, Oliver and Carmelite Thompson. Upon graduating from Seward Park High School in 1951, Montgomery worked painting faces on dolls and statues. In 1955, she married Ulysses "Jim" Montgomery and moved to Los Angeles. In California she began working for jewelry designer Thomas Usher while attending Los Angeles City College. She continued her education at California College of the Arts (California College of Arts and Crafts) where she received her Bachelor of Fine Arts degree in 1969. During the late 1960s, Montgomery began curating exhibitions. From 1971 to 1976, she was curator for Rainbow Sign Gallery in Berkeley. Other roles Montgomery held were as the national exhibits workshop coordinator at the American Association for State and Local History and as program development consultant at the African American Museums Association. From 1976 to 1979, she was art commissioner for the city of San Francisco.
Montgomery moved to Washington, D.C. in 1980 to serve as the community affairs director for Howard University's WHMM-TV station. She then began working for the United States Information Agency (USIA) as a program officer in their Arts America program in the early 1980s. In her role, she worked to promote cross-cultural exchanges through art, specializing in American exhibitions touring abroad. Montgomery retired from the USIA in 2008.
As an artist, Montgomery gained recognition for her work in printmaking and metalworking. She was the recipient of the D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities fellowship in 2012 and an Excellence in the Arts Award from the Brandywine Print Workshop in 2004. Due to her diagnosis of Parkinson's disease in the 1990s, Montgomery had to stop working with metal but continued her printmaking work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1967-2015 (1.0 linear feet; Box 1, OV 27)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1963-2014 (2.0 linear feet; Boxes 2-4)
Series 3: Professional Activity Files, 1963-2017 (7.6 linear feet; Boxes 4-11)
Series 4: Research Files and Notes, 1928-2018 (4.0 linear feet; Boxes 11-16)
Series 5: Files Regarding Montgomery's Career as an Artist, 1970-2016 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 16-17)
Series 6: Printed and Documentary Materials, 1964-2018 (7.2 linear feet; Boxes 17-23, 26, OVs 27-29, 31-34
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1957-2006 (0.2 linear feet; Boxes 23, 26, OV 30)
Series 8: Photographic Materials and Moving Images, circa 1965-2017 (3.0 linear feet; Boxes 23-27, OV 27)
Series 9: Unidentified Audiovisual Materials, circa 1990s (1 folder; Box 25)
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist, curator, and arts administrator Evangeline "EJ" Montgomery measure 26.1 linear feet and date from 1929-2019. The papers relate to Montgomery's career and involvement in the African American art scene in California and Washington, D.C. The collection includes biographical materials consisting of calendars and appointment books, certificates and awards, records regarding Montgomery's personal art collection, resumes and biographies, and other personal records; correspondence with colleagues and friends such as Benny Andrews, Willis Bing Davis, Edmund Barry Gaither, Eugene Grigsby, Dele Jegede, Samella Lewis, Nzegwu Nkiru, and A.M. Weaver; professional activity files documenting Montgomery's career as a consultant, curator, member, and volunteer for a myriad of organizations including the American Association for State and Local History, National Conference of Artists, and the Oakland Museum; and research files and notes on African and African American arts and history, Black media, Black photographers, the museum profession, and the artists Betye Saar, Lois Mailou Jones, Nike Davies-Okundaye, Romare Bearden, Ruth Waddy, Sam Gilliam, and Sargent Johnson. Also included are files regarding Montgomery's career as an artist containing material on the Brandywine Workshop, interviews with Floyd Coleman and for The Historymakers, sales and consignment records, and other material; printed and documentary material consisting of art reproductions, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and posters regarding Montgomery and other African American artists; artwork by Montgomery, including student sketchbooks, and others; photographic material of Montgomery, friends and colleagues, events, personal snapshots, and works of art; and unidentified audiovisual material.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Evangeline J. Montgomery papers were donated in 2019 by Evangeline J. Montgomery, as part of the Archives' African American Collecting Initiative funded by the Henry Luce Foundation.
Art museum curators -- Washington (D.C.); Art museum curators -- California; Printmakers -- Washington (D.C.); Metal-workers -- Washington (D.C.); African American artists; African American art museum curators; Black Arts movement; Drawings; Interviews; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Women artists; Women museum curators; Women printmakers; Metal-workers -- California; Printmakers -- California; Women arts administrators; Andrews, Benny, 1930-2006; Saar, Betye; Jones, Lois Mailou, 1905-1998; Waddy, Ruth G. (Ruth Gilliam), 1909-2003
- Biographical Materials, 1967-2015; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1, OV 27
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains 4 calendars and 13 appointments books that document Montgomery's daily activities, certificates and awards, financial and legal records, resumes and biographical writings about Montgomery, Montgomery's student records from when she attended Los Angeles City College, a file containing lists and transaction records regarding Montgomery's personal art collection, notes by Montgomery recording personal life events, and files that include born digital records regarding Montgomery's retirement from USIA and her birthday celebrations.
  - Annotated Calendars, 1976-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    4 calendars
  - Appointment Books, 1967-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-12)
    13 books
  - Birthday Celebrations, 2002-2015; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 electronic disk (CD). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Business Cards, circa 1970-circa 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1995-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 27)
  - Certificate of Birth, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial Records, 1975-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Identification Documents, 1972-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Legal Records, 1981-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes on Personal Life Events, circa 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal Art Collection, 1978-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Resumes and Biographies, circa 1965-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - Retirement Event Information and Documents, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Student Records, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1963-2014; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  The majority of correspondence is with colleagues from Montgomery's contacts at USIA, consultant work, and the many professional organizations in which she was involved. The correspondence reveals Montgomery's professional relationships, and also her many friendships with fellow colleagues in the arts who often express their admiration and gratitude towards Montgomery. Some correspondents included are Benny Andrews, Elizabeth Catlett (filed under "M" as Calett's letter is signed with her married name "Mora"), Willis Bing Davis, Edmund Barry Gaither, Eugene Grigsby, Dele Jegede, Samella Lewis, Nzegwu Nkiru, and A.M. Weaver. Also included are letters between Montgomery and her husband Ulysses, correspondence from Montgomery, and letters from correspondents by first name only.
  - A, 1970-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abajian, James, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Andrews, Benny, 1971-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes correspondence between the Whitney Museum and the Black Emergency Cultural Coalition.
  - B, 1967-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - C, 1965-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Coleman, Floyd, 1993-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - D, 1965-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Davis, Willis Bing, 1973-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes a letter of recommendation for Montgomery's fellowship application with the Howard Foundation.
  - Dockery, Glenna, 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence is between Dockery and various correspondents.
  - E, 1966-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - F, 1971-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Frontiers in Fiber" Exhibition in Beijing, Regarding, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - G, 1970-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Gaither, Edmund Barry, 1970-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Goode, Dale, circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Grigsby, Eugene, 1971-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - H, 1969-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - I, 1971-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - J-K, 1970-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jegede, Dele, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - L, 1971-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lewis, Samella, 1970-1976; 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - M, 1970-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    Includes letter from Elizabeth Catlett, signed with her married name "Mora."
  - Monroe, Arthur, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - N, 1964-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Nkiru, Nzegwu, 1995-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - O, circa 1976-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Obama, Barak, 2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - P, 1968-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Partridge, Elizabeth (Imogen Cunningham Trust), 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Q-R, 1970-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - S, 1968-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - T, 1969-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - U-V, 1963-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - W, 1968-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Weaver, A.M., 2000-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Y-Z, 1971-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - From Montgomery, 1969-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Between Montgomery, Ulysses and Evangeline Montgomery, 1965-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - First Name Only, A, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - First Name Only, B-C, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - First Name Only, C-D, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - First Name Only, E-G, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - First Name Only, H-I, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - First Name Only, J, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - First Name Only, J-L, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - First Name Only, M, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - First Name Only, N-S, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - First Name Only, S-T, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - First Name Only, V-Z, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Multiple Senders, circa 1985; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sender Envelopes, 1971-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - No Name or Illegible, 1969-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Professional Activity Files, 1963-2017; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 7.6 Linear feet Boxes 4-11
  The series documents Montgomery's career as a consultant, curator, member, and volunteer for a myriad of organizations such as the African American Museums Association, Art West Associated North, National Conference of Artists, National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Club, and Women's Caucus for Art. She also worked to promote African American artists through exhibitions, talks, conferences, events, and educational programs, and worked to cultivate cross-cultural programs in the United States of African and other international artists. Many of Montgomery's projects were done in conjunction with her role as Program Officer for the United States Information Agency (USIA). Files contain 33 video and sound recordings, 2 born digital records, meeting notes, exhibition and project planning documents, exhibition reviews and other printed materials, correspondence, budget records, and other organizational materials.
  Files for exhibitions curated by Montgomery include Black Graphics (1973-1975), Black Reflections I: The Paintings and Sculpture of Sargent Johnson / Charles Dawkins (1976), and "Images: Africa's Children" (1982). The files contain artwork lists, correspondence, loan documents, material about the artists, and other exhibition planning documents.
  Montgomery's files as National Exhibits Workshop Coordinator at the American Association for State and Local History include Exhibits Workshops Screening Committee material, a notebook regarding workshops, and material on the NEH funded Interpreting History Workshops.
  Montgomery was the Ethnic Art Consultant at the Oakland Museum from 1968 until 1974. Her files include survey records researching exhibitions of Black artists, catalog statement drafts by Montgomery for a Grafton Tyler Brown exhibition, planning and printed material for the exhibition series Black Untitled (1970-1973), and records for the museum's first large exhibition New Perspectives in Black Art (1968) at Kaiser Industries prior to the museum's opening.
  Conference files document Montgomery's participation at conferences for the College Art Association and James A. Porter Colloquium, along with video recordings of Montgomery lecturing at the October Gallery Art Seminar and Alabama State University.
  - African American Dance Project Advisory Panel, When the Spirit Moves: African American Dance in History and Art (1999), 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - African American Dance Project Advisory Panel, When the Spirit Moves: African American Dance in History and Art (1999), circa 1997; Archival Resource Key; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) Cassettes are labeled with the name of the exhibition and may contain the same recording. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - African American Museums Association, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7-11)
  - African American Museums Association, 1982; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Cassette notes recording is of exhibition design and programs workshop by Bruce G. Clarke (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Alliance of African American Artists Foundation, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - American Association for State and Local History, General, 1977-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - American Association for State and Local History, Exhibits Workshops Screening Committee, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - American Association for State and Local History, Interpreting History Workshops, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - American Association for State and Local History, Notebook on Workshops, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ark Urban Systems, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Arko Systems, Ltd., Jamal and Co., 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Art Consultant, Trickle Up Program, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Art West Associated North, 1967-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - Art West Associated North, Applications, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Black Art and Visual Culture Research Society (BAVCRS), 2000-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Blacks in Government, Evangeline J. Montgomery Scholarship Award", 2004-2017; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 electronic disk (CD). (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
  - Black Women Organized for Action, 1973-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Carnation Company, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Center for Creative Arts and Sciences, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Center for the Visual Arts, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Coalition of One Hundred Black Women of D.C., 1985-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Congressional Black Caucus Exhibition Project, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Conferences, General, 1968-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20-23)
  - Conferences, College Art Association, 80th Annual Conference, 1992; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, College Art Association, 90th Annual Conference, 2002; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) 90th Annual Conference (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Conferences, College Art Association, 2002; Archival Resource Key; 6 Sound cassettes Notes on cassettes: "The Daring Eye: The History of African American Photography," "From Brushstrokes to Bytes: Art Historical Approaches to Digital Art," "Foundations in Art: Theory and Education: Globalizing Foundations: Expanding the Core to Include Non-Western...," and "Nonfunctional Crafts: Does the Argument Hold Water?" (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Conferences, Montgomery's Lecture for October Gallery Art Seminar at Temple University, 1987; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Conferences, Lecture Notes and Program Information, 1968-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, Montgomery's Talk at Alabama State University, 1979; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Conferences, James A. Porter Colloquium, 2000-2002; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Contacts and Mailing Lists, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
  - Contacts and Mailing Lists, circa 1970-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Contemporary Crafts Inc., 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - District of Columbia Arts Center (DCAC), 1989-2014; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 electronic disk (DVD). (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Duke Ellington School of the Arts Evaluation, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Consultant, "Early Black Newspapers" at Cheyney State College (1981-1982), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Curator, Black Graphics (1973-1975), Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Curator, Black Reflections I: The Paintings and Sculpture of Sargent Johnson / Charles Dawkins (1976), 1973-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Curator, "Images: Africa's Children" (1982), 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Festival of Black Arts and Culture (FESTAC), 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Festival of Black Arts and Culture (FESTAC), "Black Renaissance" KBHK Television Program, 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Festival of Black Arts and Culture (FESTAC), KQED, 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Fillmore and Fell Corporation, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - First National African American Crafts Conference and Jubilee Proposal, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - General Professional Activity Records, circa 1970-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Grant Project, "Black Women in the Visual Arts: Past and Present," Directory, 1971-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17-20)
  - Howard University, 1982-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Howard University, WHMM-TV, 1980-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Howard University, WHMM-TV, Dr. Epko Eyo, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Howard University, WHMM-TV, Host Project, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - ICA, Stephen Prince Music Arrangements, 1988; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Lists, Artwork and Artists and Galleries, 1970-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Sculpture Competition Selection Committee, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Membership Cards and Certificates, circa 1970-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)